Guide to the Freeling Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Freeling correspondence
1794-1841
OSB MSS 36
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
Letters to Freeling, mainly concerning his work for the postal service. Some letters contain a draft of Freeling's reply.
Freeling, Francis, Sir, 1764-1836
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SIR FRANCIS FREELING, 1764-1836
Sir Francis Freeling was born in Radcliffe Parish, Bristol, on August 25, 1764. His first employment was with the Bristol Post Office, but when the new Palmer system of mail coaches was established in 1785, Freeling was appointed to assist Palmer. In 1787 he joined the General Post Office in London, where he served for almost half a century, rising finally to the office of Sole Secretary.
Freeling's management of the postal service was widely praised, and in 1828 a baronetcy was conferred on him for his public service. He was also a book collector and antiquarian, a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries and a founding member of the Roxburghe Club. He died at home in Bryanston Square, London, in 1836, and was succeeded in the baronetcy by his eldest son, Sir George Henry Freeling, an Oxford alumnus and Commissioner of Customs.
Scope and Contents
The Freeling Correspondence consists almost entirely of business letters addressed to Sir Francis Freeling as an employee of the Post Office. The letters are mostly by members of the peerage, suggesting that they may have been selected from Freeling's files and saved for their autograph value. Authors include the Earl of Arran, the Duke of Beaufort, the Duke of Buckingham and Chandos, Lord Elcho, and the Earl of Chichester. Subjects include franking privileges; mail routes and mail delivery times; delayed or lost mail; recommendations for employment; and requests for favors. Some of the letters are docketed with summaries of Freeling's replies.
Among the more substantive items are a letter from the Earl of Cardigan concerning a large theft by a servant; complaints by Baron Dulcie of repeatedly delayed mail; and an MP's complaint that his franks are not being honored. An 1809 letter from Edward Cooke, Undersecretary of State for War, explains the Army's position on mail privileges for officers "it is a matter of much accommodation to the officer and the loss to revenue is but casual." And a letter from Freeling himself to the Postmasters-General in 1810 takes issue with an anonymous complaint about working conditions in the Post Office, noting that "the Income of the Letter Carriers, considering the order in Society from which they are selected and the duty they have to perform, is sufficiently ample."
Postal service -- Great Britain; Freeling, Francis, Sir, 1764-1836
- Correspondence, 1794-1841; Series I; 0.21' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - ARBUTHNOT, CHARLES, 1767-1850
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Treasury Chambers, 1818 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Arbuthnot, citing his franking privileges, complains letters have returned to him.
  - ARRAN, ARTHUR SAUNDERS, EARL OF, 1761-1837
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling, 1815 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Informs Freeling of his support for a Mr. Bosauquet's election to an unnamed club or position.
  - AUCKLAND, WILLIAM EDEN, LORD, 1744-1814
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Eden Farm, 1803 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS to Francis Freeling; Eden Farm, [1808 Dec 27] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Holiday greetings to the Freelings from the Aucklands, who plan to "settle" in town from 18 Jan to 10 May.
  - BARRY, JOHN M.
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Treasury Chambers, Dublin Castle, 1818 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Barry requests Freeling to hold some postal packets for him. Freeling's reply (copy) is included on the letter.
  - BEAUFORT, HENRY CHARLES SOMERSET, DUKE OF, 1766-1835
    - ALS to Francis Freeling; Grosvenor Square, 1828 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Concerning Beaufort's mother's suggestion to leave a letter bag at her gate at Stoke near Bristol.
  - BUCKINGHAM AND CHANDOS, RICHARD TEMPLE
    [NUGENT BRYDGES CHANDOS GRENVILLE, DUKE OF, 1776-1839]
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Pall Mall, 1834 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Chandos requests delivery of a letter of the "utmost importance."
  - CARDIGAN, ROBERT BRUDENELL, EARL OF, 1769-1837
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Portman Square, 1827 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      States that Wm. Upton has absconded with a very large sum of money.
  - CARYSFORT, JOHN JOSHUA PROBY, EARL OF, 1751-1828
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Archlow [Ireland], 1809 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Carysfort asks Freeling to frank, "on a literary matter, a pretty bulky packed [sent] to Mr. George Ellis, at Sunning Hill or Clarenont."
  - CAWDOR, JOHN FREDERICK, EARL OF, 1790-1860
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Stackpole Court, 1828 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Cawdor inquires about the route of mail between London and Cork, Ireland. Note on Docket states Dublin.
  - CHAMPION DE CRESPIGNY, WILLIAM, SIR, 1765-1829
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Southampton, 1818 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      De Crespigny seeks Freeling's aid.
  - CHARTERIS, FRANCIS, (LORD ELCHO), 1749-1808
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Grosvenor Street, 1794 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CHESTERFIELD, HENRIETTA (THYNNE) STANHOPE
    [COUNTESS OF, 1762-1813]
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Chesterfield House, 1803 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Lady Chesterfield lobbies for the appointment of a Mr. Dunn as letter carrier.
  - CHICHESTER, MARY HENRIETTA JULIANA (GODOLPHIN)
    [PELHAM, COUNTESS OF, 1776-1862]
    - 2 ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Stanmer, 1809 Aug, Sep (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Concerning the 5th birthday celebration of her eldest son Henry (b. 25 Aug 1804).
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Stanmer, 1818 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Concerning her husband Lord Chichester's cold which has kept him three days abed.
  - CIPRIANI, [PHILIP]
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Treasury, 1809 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Cipriani recommends a Mr. Knowles for employment. Copy of Freeling's response on reverse side.
  - CLAYTON, WILLIAM ROBERT, SIR, 1786-1866
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1816 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Clayton warns Freeling that a letter with Freeling's frank mailed to Calais had produced a charge of postage due there and Freeling is admonished not to allow such a precedent to be set.
  - COOKE, EDWARD, 1755-1820
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Downing Street, 1809 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Cooke, Undersecretary of State for War and colonies, concerning abuses of the mail by the army and foreign services.
  - CURREY, EDMUND
    - 2 ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Bath and Bankhouse, 1808, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Currey writes on behalf of the Duke of Gloucester.
  - DERBY, EDWARD SMITH STANLEY, EARL OF, 1752-1834
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Grosvenor Square, 1806 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Derby thanks Freeling for his attention in securing a Post Mastership for an individual.
  - DULCIE, FRANCIS REYNOLDS-MORETON, BARON, 1739-1808
    - LS to Sir Francis Freeling; Tortworth, 1794 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Dulcie complains about postal service delays.
  - FREELING, FRANCIS, SIR, 1764-1836
    - Letter (copy) to Charles Arbuthnot, General Post Office, 1818 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letter (copy) to Mr. Hindell at Truro, [n.p.], 1810 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Freeling states: "... an Official Man cannot indulge those feelings and inclinations which would at once influence him as a Private Individual.
    - Letter to [the Earls of Chichester and Sandwich], General Post Office, 1810 Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Chichester and Sandwich, serving in 1810 as Postmasters-General. Freeling's letter concerns an anonymous letter of complaint, apparently from a letter carrier. Docketed response from Chichester urges Freeling to "attempt ... to discover the writer of this letter."
  - GARDINER, ROBERT WILLIAM, SIR, 1781-1864
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Cassell, 1818 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - GREVILLE, CHARLES FRANCIS, 1749-1809
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Stackpole Court, 1798 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - GREVILLE, ROBERT FULKE, 1751-1824
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Mayfair, 1818 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - HARTWELL, FRANCIS JOHN, SIR, 1757-1831
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Dorchester, 1818 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - HOBHOUSE, HENRY, 1776-1854
    - ALS to Francis Freeling; Whitehall, 1818 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - ALS to Lt. Col. William Leader Maberly, Wincanton, 1841 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - JONES, WILLIAM
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Cassel, 1818 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - MALMESBURY, JAMES HARRIS, EARL OF, 1746-1820
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Huru Court, Christchurch, 1806 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - PELHAM, THOMAS, EARL OF CHICHESTER, 1756-1826
    - 3 ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Eridge Castle and Stanmer, 1818 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - POLE, L. S.
    - ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Oxford Street, 1816 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 34)